Rhiannon: Individuals who work with
children and young people play a crucial
role in shaping their lives and are
responsible for managing risks, using
the correct resources, establishing a
safe environment and safeguarding them
from harm or unprofessional conduct.
Leah: Children and young people have
a right to be treated with respect
and dignity and It follows, that
trusted adults are expected to take
reasonable steps to ensure the safety
and well-being of children and young
people as part of that ‘duty of care’.
Rhiannon: All workplaces, whether a
school, a care provider or justice
service organisation have a moral and a
legal obligation to ensure that everyone
associated with that establishment,
whether employee, volunteer, student,
tradesperson or the general public,
is fully protected from any personal
physical or emotional harm, either
on the premises or when engaged in
activities relating to that establishment.
Leah: Typical areas of concern are
fire safety, health and safety,
food safety, personal safety, child
and adult protection, safeguarding
such as safer recruitment, equality,
bullying, violence, harassment, stress,
or discrimination from any source.
Rhiannon: A breach of ‘duty of care’
occurs when a person or an organisation
fails to live up to that standard.
A person may be liable for negligence
in a personal injury case if their
breach of duty caused another person's
injuries or mental ill health.
Leah: In education ‘duty of care’
is measured as being that of a
‘reasonable parent’ as when parents
leave their child at the school gates,
they are in effect agreeing to allow
the teachers and other staff at the
school to act ‘in loco parentis’.
Rhiannon: This means, that ‘in place of a
parent’, all teachers, including trainees,
have a 'duty of care' towards their pupils
and are required to apply their education
and acquired skills to safeguard pupils.
Leah: Any facilities need to be safe
and fit for purpose and all pupils
of all abilities have the right to
be protected from harm, especially
those who may be vulnerable.
For example, if a school arranges
trips, there needs to be enough
help and support to keep all
children safe with all potential
risks assessed.
Rhiannon: A care provider is expected
to be trustworthy, and act in
accordance with their code of practice.
They should be up to date with
knowledge and skills and ensure that
service is provided safely, and records
up-to-date, accurate and confidential
except where the wider duty of care
or public interest might at risk.
Leah: In the criminal justice system,
the aim is for every child to have a
safe and crime-free life and make a
positive contribution to society with a
focus on child first, offender second.
Rhiannon: To maintain ‘duty of
care’ all inspectors should make
sure that youth justice services
meet statutory requirements, and
no one is taken advantage of.
Leah: All individuals working with
children and young people need
to understand and acknowledge the
responsibilities and trust inherent
in their role and do what a reasonable
person, with their training and
background, can be expected to
do, to maintain a duty of care.